e
e e
good evening everyone
it's 6:30 and I now call to order this
February 11th 2025 meeting of Lancaster
City Council a few things at the top of
the meeting first an announcement uh we
had an executive session it was held
this evening Tuesday February
2025th um February 11th 2025 excuse me
uh this evening at 6 pm at council
chambers City Hall to discuss personnel
and legal matters related to a pension
disability request of Michael deets
thank you council president oh that's
later sorry I'm gonna that's gonna that
will appear in our legislative agenda
this evening I'm going to continue with
my other reminders at the top of the
meeting uh this meeting and its
participants are being recorded please
take a moment to silence your phones and
other devices as a courtesy to others if
you haven't done so already during this
meeting there will be several
opportunities for public comment anyone
making comment to do so at the
microphone uh right in front of you
there so that you can be heard comments
should be related to issues that have or
may come before Council as legislative
items and should be addressed toward
Council rather than to others in the
room each speaker will be given three
minutes to keep time you will see the
light here in front of me turn green
when a speaker begins it'll turn yellow
when there's one minute remaining and it
will turn green when three minutes has
been exhausted thank you to everyone in
advance for ensuring that everyone has
equal time and now for all of those who
are willing and able please rise for the
Pledge of Allegiance
I Alle to the flag of the United States
of America and to the Republic stands
one nation under God indivisible with
liy and justice for
all Mr Harris would you please call the
role of members yes Madam president Mr M
here Mr Royo here Mr GLE here M Craig
here m yes here Mr HH here president B
here we'll now move to the approval of
the minutes of the January 28th 2025
regular meeting of council motion to
approve second we have a motion and a
second are there any Council comments on
the
minutes hearing none Mr Harris Mr Man I
Mr royya I Mr Glee I Mr Craig i m Diaz I
Mr hirsh I and president b
i the next item on our agenda are
proclamations honors Awards and
resolutions of recognition which we have
W this evening resolution number nine
2025 Mr
Harris yes Madam president the
resolution of the Council of the city of
Lancaster do designating February 2025
as Black History Month in the city of
Lancaster and recognizing resistance to
Injustice Injustice by African-Americans
throughout Lancaster history motion to
approve second we have a motion and a
second councelor Craig council president
um this resolution was read into record
during the committee meeting last week
and I don't feel the need to reread it
because it's quite
lengthy thank you councelor Craig and
thank you for reading that into our
meeting record um and we thank uh you
and the work that you did uh together um
as with previous years this was drafted
with the help of the local chapter of
the
NAACP are there any additional comments
uh Council comments on the
resolution council president if I may
councelor Amed I just want to thank
councelor Craig for uh introducing this
resolution and I want to thank the city
of Lancaster for its commitment to
celebrating Black History Month uh
especially in a Time nationally uh where
it does not seem to be prioritized so I
just want to thank members of Council uh
and thank the city for its uh commitment
to our black community here in Langster
thank you councilor armed additional
comments from members of
council from the public on the
resolution hearing none Mr Harris Mr Med
I Mr Royo hi Mr Glee I M Craig i m Diaz
I Mr h I and president B I thank
you the next item on our agenda is
public comment this is section reserved
for residents who have contacted the
city clerk prior to the meeting to
request the opportunity to address city
council again duration of comments is
limited to three minutes per speaker um
just confirming uh Mr Harris are there
any public comments uh for this period
no Madam president no one no one uh
contacted me in advance of the meeting
thank you very much um then we'll we'll
move on to our next agenda item this
evening which is reports requested by
Council uh I don't believe we have any
of those is that correct Mr Harris that
is correct thank you the next item on
our agenda is reports of Committees of
council these are the meetings held on
February 3rd
2025 we begin with the Public Safety
Committee councelor
Diaz the public safety did not meet
thank you councelor Diaz Public Works
committee Council hirsh thank you
president the Public Works committee had
three agenda items um all of which will
be seen in our um in our agenda this
evening here at Council uh resolution 10
authorizing cost sharing agreement
Witham Township um and resolutions 15
and 16 which are seeking approval for
use of right of way um their permit
applications and agreements that are to
be made with um Railway auditing
Management Services in Northfolk
Southern um and that concludes the
report the Public Works committee thank
you councelor H Economic Development
Committee councelor Amed thank you
council president the economic
development committee did not meet thank
you finance committee Council Royo thank
you council president uh the finance
committee did meet we had three items on
our agenda for that evening uh we
discussed resolution number 1225
amending the supplemental pension plan
for city employees and resolution number
1325 exonerating of utility fees excuse
me exoneration of utility Fe fees both
of those items will be on the agenda
later this evening we also received an
update on a bond insurance from director
Campbell uh she gave an overview of an
upcoming General obligation Bond
issuance that will be brought forward to
Council in a proposed ordinance the bond
issue will be for a total of 53 excuse
me $ 55.3 million and the debt will be
divided among the general fund water
fund and Sewer fund uh next month we
will also have a list a list of the
projects that will be funded by the bond
issue that concludes my report council
president thank you councelor Oro
Community planning committee councelor
Craig thank you council president
Community planning did meet we had one
item on the agenda that was
Administration resolution 1425 adopting
substantial amendments to community de
Community Development block grant annual
action plan that will come up on our
agenda our legislative agenda in and
just a little B thank you very much
councelor Craig and Personnel committee
councelor kle thank you Madame President
the personal committee did meet on
February 3rd and review a nomination to
reappointment to the city revitalization
and Improvement Zone Authority that
conclude my reports thank you very much
we'll now move into our legislative
agenda uh the first item is uh an
authorization of action this is related
to our executive session um and uh this
would be authorizing or denying a
request for Disability Pension for
Michael Deets um I believe Council Craig
you wanted to address this thank you
upon recommendation of the Bureau of
police officers relief the police
pension board city council met in an exe
executive session to review the
Disability Pension application of
Michael Deets based upon the unanimous
recommendation of the police of the
Bureau of police officers relief and the
information provided to counselors
during the executive session
I hereby make a move to approve Michael
de's application for a Disability
Pension second thank you Council Craig
we have a motion and a second to approve
the request are there any Council
comments on the
motion from the
public hearing none Mr Harris Mr Med I
Mr royya hi Mr Glee hi M Craig Hi M Diaz
I Mr hirsh hi and president B
I move into the second item on our
legislative agenda this evening these
are nominations for appointments
councelor CLE leave you have item thank
you Madame President this nomination was
this was reviewed on February 3rd by U
um the personal committee and full conso
now I'll make a motion to reappoint the
Shelby Norman to the city revitalization
and Improvement Zone Authority for a
term from December 31st 2024 to December
31st
2029 second we have a motion and a
second on the appointment uh any
additional Council comments for the
appointment of Miss
nman from the public
hearing none Mr Harris Mr M i Mr Royo I
Mr Glee I Mr Greg i m Diaz I Mr hirs I
president b
i next item is item C resolutions we
begin with Administration resolution
number 10 2025 Mr Harris a resolution to
the Council of the city of Lancaster
approving an intermunicipal agreement
for cost sharing of Marshall Avenue
roadway base repairs between Manheim
Township and the city of
Lancaster motion to approve second we
have a motion and a second this is
coming through public works councelor
hsh thank you council president um this
resolution is essentially uh entering
the city into a cost sharing agreement
with manam Township um as many of you
may know uh Marshall Avenue is along the
northern border and Southern uh of the
city and the southern border of mayheim
Township um and it zigzags pretty
chaotically and so this kind of allows
the city to enter into into an agreement
where um they are taking on the portion
of the cost that uh is proportionate to
the city's ownership of the road which
in this case um these improvements are
primarily going to be to
improve uh biking and walking
infrastructure along Marshall AV total
cost is roughly
62,000 um so it's a pretty uh lowcost
project on the whole um the city is
going to take 82% of that as they own
82% of that roadway um it's not a full
resurfacing project it's base
improvements um to the roadway to allow
the additional infrastructure to be put
in um and my understanding is that the
work is uh slated to take place later
this year is that correct uh director
Campbell is nodding um so that's pretty
much uh the deal with with this rone
thank you very much Council h uh I'll
just say whoever figured out that we
owned 82% specifically of the road at
kudos to them spent a lot of time in GIS
I bet yeah uh any additional Council
comments on the
resolution from the
public hearing none Mr Harris Mr red I
Mr Royo hi Mr Glee hi Miss Craig hi Miss
Diaz hi Mr HH I president p
i the next item is Administration
resolution number 11
2025 Mr Harris a resolution to the
Council of the city of Lancaster
approving the pride flag raising to
acknowledge the start of pride month in
June 2025 as brought forth by the
Lancaster Pride Association motion to
approve second we have a motion and a
second uh members of council thank you
so much for allowing allowing me to
introduce this resolution
um this is for a flag raising that will
take place on June 2nd 2025 with the
inclement weather date of June 3rd
2025 um the uh the request was submitted
in a timely manner and um we uh look
forward to raising the flag again this
coming June for pride
month there any additional Council
comments on the
resolution from the public
hearing none Mr Harris Mr M i Mr royya I
Mr GLE I miss Craig Craig
I miss Diaz I Mr hirs
I and president Baker
I all right our next item on the agenda
is resolution number 12
2025 Mr Harris a resolution of the city
of the city of Lancaster Lancaster
County Pennsylvania amending the city of
Lancaster's supplemental pension plan in
order to reflect that the effective
January 1st
2023 I'm sorry that effective January
1st 2023 the matching percentage with
respect to a police officer hired on or
before on or after January 1 2011 became
equal to 35% of the amount contributed
by the participant motion to approve
second we have a motion and a second on
the resolution this is coming through
the finance committee councelor Royo
thank you council president uh director
Campbell uh went through this resolution
during our last finance committee
meeting um we are amending the city of
Lancaster supplemental pension plan to
reflect the correct amount of matching
contribution for police officers hired
on or after January 1 of 2011 the plan
currently incorrectly states that this
is a 25 this is 25%
so this resolution will correct the
matching contribution amount to 35% we
reinstated the plan last year at this
time in February of 2024 with the
inclusion then of firefighters who were
included starting in January 2024
however we didn't make the correct uh
the excuse me however we failed to make
the correct to the matching percentage
for police at that time um this
resolution will correct
that thank you very much Council Royo
are there any additional Council
comments on the
resolution from the
public hearing none Mr Harris Mr Med I
Mr Royo I Mr GLE I miss Greg I miss Diaz
I Mr Hirsch I president b
i we will now move to Administration
resolution number 13 2025 Mr Harris a
resolution of the of the Council of the
city of Lancaster exonerating 224 water
charges in the amount of
$63,750 and Sewer charges in the amount
of $
64,0 64 for City owned or related
properties at 25
locations motion to approve second we
have a motion and a second uh councelor
Royo thank you council president uh this
is a resolution that is brought before
Council on an annual basis um it is done
because the city tracks water and sew
sewer usage at City properties mostly to
detect leaks or unusual usage we don't
Bill ourselves for this usage the
charges are exagerated annually to clear
them from the financial accounts two
properties on the list are not
city-owned the library and the fire line
at the Lancaster Airport the water and
the sewer service to the library is
considered an in-kind contribution from
the city and the service to the airport
is done in exchange for the airport
providing the city use of its large
capacity snowblowers in case of a major
snowstorm thank you very much Council
Roo are there any additional uh Council
comments on the
resolution from the
public hearing none Mr Harris Mr Med hi
Mr royya hi Mr Glee I miss CG all right
Miss Diaz I Mr hirch I president b
i we'll now move to resolution number 14
2025 Mr Harris a resolution of the
Council of the city of Lancaster
authorizing the mayor to submit
substantial amendments for the following
documents one the combined
2021 to 2025 Consolidated plan and the
2021 annual action plan and two the 2022
annual action plan and three the 2023
annual action plan and four the 2024
annual action plan to the US Department
of Housing and Urban Development the
submission includes projected changes in
the use of funds for the Community
Development block grant program during
the 2021 2022
2023 and 2024
program motion to approve second we have
a motion and a second councelor Craig
thank you council president as presented
by deputy director geyser and Community
Development administrator Jen rumel at
um committee
meeting on the 3 they are recommending
substantial amendments to each of the
annual action plans from for 2021
through
2024 the proposed amendments to the
program would increase funding for the
critical repair program and Lead Hazard
Reduction Program
administrations administrations
by administrations by
199,000 Community facilities by
75,000 and affordable housing
Solutions approximately
35,200 also in the presentation listed
are the four areas that would see
reduction primarily due to spending caps
within the cdbg program that that was
presented by
um deputy director geyser and Jen rumel
and if there's any questions I see that
um Miss geyser is here thank you very
much councelor Craig Miss Geer do you
have anything to
add yes thank you thanks for the summary
uh the lengthy summary of our long
amendments um this evening I just wanted
to uh highlight two things
um that we are recommending these
changes presuming that we will get the
2025 cdbg funding for the city uh
however with the uncertainty in the
federal government uh the federal
allocations for cdbg may change and if
our allocation significantly changes we
would have to um reassess our
substantial amendments and potentially
come back to you with additional changes
which we try not to do but uh that may
be required if there is an unexpected
decrease um next year um I also wanted
to note that last week we received a
question about our total efforts toward
affordable housing since we are
reallocating about 300,000 to affordable
housing and I wanted to provide just a
snapshot of the total dollars the city
has invested in affordable housing
because it's just astronomical and
noteworthy um so since 2018 uh we have
allocated $8.1 million for $492 lead
Hazard control projects $1.5 million for
152 home repair projects $4.4 million
for 363 units of affordable housing that
was rehabilitated and $1.6 million for
for
284 new affordable housing units and the
grand total is $25.6
million invested in affordable housing
um representing a commitment by you the
city council and the mayor to this
initiative and uh although we are only
able to reallocate 300,000 across 5
years the total allocation is more than
a million dollars over the five years
just from cdbg Alone um and we been able
to accomplish this unprecedented funding
by allocated allocating small amounts
large amounts big grants small grants
throughout all these years um to
accumulate to this total so wanted to
just bring that to your attention and
thank you all again for your commitment
to affordable housing over all the
years thank you very much Rebecca and
thank you for that summary I think
that's important to keep that in
perspective yeah little projects and big
projects
yes um additional comments from Council
on the
resolution from the
public I have a
question good
evening good evening Susie Gomez 100
block of North Reservoir Street thank
you um can you explain to me uh cbbg
funding is that Government funding yes
that's Federal Government funding okay
so total of investment of you said 25.6
million the 25.6 million that I was
referencing just now was the amount of
affordable housing investment we've made
since 2018 to 2024 across many different
funding streams um the cdbg
allocation is about $1.5 million per
Year and that is government funding
correct yes okay um the other question
would be um you had
mentioned
[Music]
uh increase funding the
305,000 is being allocated is that
correct realloc reallocated so you're
going from 202 to
2024 to show rejected
funds can you explain that a little
better this G is just to make sure you
keep your time as there anything further
that you'd like misser to
explain just she can explain it now
that's that's why I'm asking great just
want yeah M
yes so due to changes over the past four
years in spending mostly due to caps and
staff vacancies we have needed to uh
change how we anticipated to spend the
money uh to what is realistic at this
point today and so this these changes
represent reallocating money that we had
previously allocated or Council had
previously allocated from 2021 to 2024
and shifting them from one bucket of
into other buckets and primarily
critical repair and Lead Hazard control
and affordable
housing thank you Miss gu
yes so one last question um you want to
reassess and make changes for
What from what for
what you're
reassessing these fundings from the
years I may Endeavor to to answer the
question so we are required to update
these plans as funds are reallocated
into these different categories so are
doing that with this measure yeah but
you're turning it in you're you're also
re uh doing the annual action plan right
you're taking all that into
consideration
without so meaning that there is funds
available for
housing and that's what these funds for
is that correct Miss
Geer we are reallocating unspent funds
from St Staffing vacancies over the past
four years into affordable housing and
Lead Hazard control and critical repair
projects so they're getting more money
the affordable housing and critical
repair projects are receiving more
funding out of administrative costs and
into the actual affordable housing yes
thank
you so my point very quickly was just
that because of that there's funding
available we have a housing crisis in
Lancaster
City and I think that is very unfair to
the
public any additional public comments on
[Music]
resolution hearing none and before we
vote I'll just make clear to council as
Miss geyser reiterated twice during her
presentation that these are funds that
are being reallocated into affordable
housing supportive products and out of
administrative
costs Mr Harris Mr M uh Mr Roy
hi Mr g i m gr hi Miss di hi Mr H hi and
pres b
i the next item on our legislative
agenda is Administration resolution
number 15 2025 Mr Harris a resolution of
the Council of the city of Lancaster
authorizing the mayor to sign the
Standford pipe lease I'm sorry pipe
license agreement between North Southern
Railway company and remit payment of
$5,000 for fees
required to the license agreement on
behalf of the city of
Lancaster motion to approve second we
have a motion and second Council hsh
thank you council president uh
resolutions number 15 and 16 are very
similar in nature um they are
essentially agreements that
um give us are we are essentially
approving um the ability to use the
right of way uh to do future
infrastructure um projects in this case
it's a ductile um pipe that is uh in
Columbia Pennsylvania is part of our
water infrastructure there um and so
applying and paying this permit fee
essentially allows uh that work to be
done
um that's really all there is to this
thank you very much councilor h are
there any additional comments on the
resolution from
Council from the
public hearing none Mr Harris Mr mitt uh
Mr Royal hi Mr please i m k i m Diaz I
Mr H hi and president b
i next item on the agenda is
Administration resolution number 16 2025
Mr Harris a resolution of the Council of
the city of Lancaster authorizing the
mayor to sign a standard pight license
agreement between Railway auditing and
management
servicesit payment of $
6,750 for fees required in the license
agreement on behalf of the city of
Lancaster motion to
approve second we have a motion and a
second Council hsh this sounds similar
yes pretty much the same thing um it's
just entering into an agreement with
Railway auditing and Management Services
in this case as opposed to norol
Southern which is previous resolution um
yeah just paying the permit fee to allow
rate of uh use to um replace or to to uh
conduct work there
so thank you very much any additional
Council comments on resolution
16 from the public
hearing none Mr Harris Mr M uh Mr Royo I
Mr please i m c i missis I Mr hi and
pres Baker
I that concludes our legislative agenda
if I'm following along correctly and
we'll take us to our second public
comment period this evening this is open
for comments on issues not previously on
the agenda duration of comments is
limited to 3 minutes per speaker and
please begin with your name and block of
residents for our meeting record if
anyone wishes to make public comment
please come up to the podium at this
time all right hearing none we'll close
the second public comment period this
evening and we will move to our next
item which is the report of the mayor
mayor s uh thank you council president
uh first I'm pleased to share that the
city of Lancaster along with the school
district of Lancaster was awarded 74
,000 by the Pennsylvania Commission on
crime and delinquency the state Grant
will allow uh school district and
partners to research and design an
effective cross- sector intervention
strategy to reduce gun and group related
violence in Lancaster and I'm truly
grateful for our partnership with the
district additionally applications for
uh police officers and Cadet uh
positions are now open we are eager to
bring on new officers and Cadets the
cadet program as you know Bridges the
gap between High School graduation and
um turning 21 uh for those who are
interested in pursuing a career in law
enforcement the application just opened
on February 1st and we have 77 officer
applications so far and 260 people who
have expressed interest encourage all of
you to help us get the word out so thank
you in advance and check out lcbp
careers.com for more information and
second I want to Spotlight the
department of neighborhood engagement
it's become a tradition that on
Valentine's Day which is coming up on on
Friday and I know everybody's just sing
about the Eagles parade but do not
forget your Valentine's um the
department announces on new initiatives
and launches applications for their
long-standing programs the state o love
your block grants are back now entering
its seventh year the program Awards
grants to Residents dedicated to
revitalizing their neighborhoods through
community-led projects love your block
is made possible through the generous
support of the high Foundation uh we're
also launching the neighborhood art
project uh which is designed to
encourage public art and creative
placemaking in our neighborhoods so a
call for artists will also go out on
February 14th inviting local artists to
apply for opportunities to create public
art that reflects the vibrancy and
diversity of linkter community the
neighborhood art project is supported by
the National Endowment for the Arts and
you can learn more about these programs
and apply to take part at city of
linger. goov neighborhoods that
concludes my report tonight thank you
council president thank you mayor sarach
uh the next item on the agenda is the
report of President of council I do not
have a report to make this evening uh so
we'll move to our next item which is
Council comments are there any Council
comments this evening talk president if
I may councilor um I just wanted to
report back to the members of council
that the government study transition
committee did meet on January 29th and
went over the purview of our work which
is to make sure and ensure the
transition to a home Ral Charter moves
in a timely manner uh with both the
administrative code and the ethics
commission our next meeting will be
Tuesday April 29th at 5:00 pm in council
chambers it'll also be live streamed um
and I just wanted to report back that we
did meet uh and uh the purview of our
work is to ensure the timely transition
to uh the newly elected home Rule
Charter that concludes my report thank
you councilor Med and I appreciate you
taking the time to serve on that
important board
any additional Council
comments hearing n have reached the end
of our agenda this evening I'll hear a
motion to adjourn motion to adjourn
second all in favor I we adjourn thank
you every
so I was reading